<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.6.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-10-05T20:27:27+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title>Data Science Rookie</title><subtitle>The journey of a data science rookie from knowing nothing to ...who knows where.</subtitle><entry><title>What Kind Of Data Scientist Do You Want To Be?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/what-kind-of-data-scientist-do-you-want-to-be/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Kind Of Data Scientist Do You Want To Be?" /><published>2017-09-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-09-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/what-kind-of-data-scientist-do-you-want-to-be</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/what-kind-of-data-scientist-do-you-want-to-be/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Data Scientist (n.): Person who is better at statistics than any software engineer and better at software engineering than any statistician.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/josh-wills-13882b/&quot;&gt;Josh Wills&lt;/a&gt;, Director of Data Engineering at Slack&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During an introductory &lt;a href=&quot;http://quarter.cs.stir.ac.uk/courses/ITNPBD4/lectures/1-What%20is%20Data%20Science.pdf&quot;&gt;What Is Data Science?&lt;/a&gt; lecture at the start of my course, one of the questions that was raised was ‘&lt;em&gt;What are the skills that a data scientist needs?&lt;/em&gt;’ (It was also a question posed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/markjhunter/&quot;&gt;Mark Hunter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/sandy-scott-2912813/&quot;&gt;Sandy Scott&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sainsburysbank.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Sainsbury’s Bank&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datascientist2-0.com&quot;&gt;Data Scientist 2.0 event&lt;/a&gt; two weeks ago.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-skills-do-data-scientists-need&quot;&gt;What skills do data scientists need?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential list is huge, comprising skills across maths/statistics, programming, databases, domain expertise, soft skills, communication and visualisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first reaction was the thought, &lt;em&gt;‘How am I supposed to get good at all that stuff in the next twelve months?’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second thought was, &lt;em&gt;‘How can &lt;strong&gt;anyone&lt;/strong&gt; be good at all that, no matter how long they’ve got to learn it?’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, no one can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s all about the skills in the &lt;em&gt;team&lt;/em&gt; rather than the individual. (A brief aside: what percentage of data scientists actually work in a team of other data scientists, and how many work alone?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This got me thinking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how do my existing skills fit with the skills required of a data scientist?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what skills do I need to develop more?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what kind of data scientist do I think I could be?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What would be a good fit for my skills, values and interests?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what kind of data scientist do I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to be?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-kind-of-data-scientist-might-i-be&quot;&gt;What kind of data scientist might I be?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harlan Harris, one of the organisers of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datacommunitydc.org/&quot;&gt;Data Community DC&lt;/a&gt;, in Washington D.C, surveyed a group of data scientists about how they viewed their own skills, described in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/analyzing-the-analyzers&quot;&gt;‘Analysing the Analysers’&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chart below shows how the data scientist self-identify. This chart was shown to us during our lecture, and of course my first thought was &lt;em&gt;‘Which one am I?’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://d3ansictanv2wj.cloudfront.net/images/3-SkillsSelfDMosaic-2-6c755564.png&quot; alt=&quot;Skills and Self-ID Top Factors&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one I feel is the best fit for me is that of &lt;strong&gt;Data Creative&lt;/strong&gt;. Of course, I’ve got the next year to figure out what’s the best fit for me, but at the moment this is my best guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-data-creative&quot;&gt;Why Data Creative?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, first off, I think of myself of a creative person. I’m interested in solving problems, specifically problems that impact on people’s lives (rather than esoteric, abstract problems - I don’t give a hoot about those). I’m the kind of person that asks, &lt;em&gt;‘How could we make this better?’&lt;/em&gt; I want to use data science to help people improve their lives. I want to use data as a force for good. That takes creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the role of Data Creative (as described here at least) is a balanced one, requiring a range of skills, but where no single skill dominates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, I like the amount of programming that’s shown within this category. I enjoy coding. It’s a great tool. However, I’m never going to be the most techie guy in the room, nor would I want to be. And I certainly wouldn’t want most of my work-life to be spent coding. That’s just not for me. That said, one skill-set I have that I believe could be useful is that of software engineering, and managing software engineering projects. I’ve managed the delivery of software products before and could foresee myself playing a useful role in delivering data products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are, however, a couple of aspects of the Data Creative I’d change to to fit my personal skills. The ‘Business’ skills section I would make bigger. I can relate well to business people and can speak in their language. Through talking to some people in data science recruitment, this appears to be a skill that’s not always evident in data science candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, two vital skills for data scientists aren’t shown in the chart at all, namely &lt;em&gt;communication&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;visualisation&lt;/em&gt;. I believe I’m a strong communicator. Visualisation (as far as data science goes) is the art of making the complex understandable. I’m sure I’ve got lots to learn here, but communicating with stakeholders/clients/colleagues (including communcating results) is fundamental to the art and science of creating actionable insights from data, and a skill I look forward to developing further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What kind of data scientist are you? What kind do you &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to be?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="skills" /><summary>What skills do data scientists need? Are there different kinds of data scientist? What kind do I want to be?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000{&quot;feature&quot;=&gt;&quot;feature_image5.jpg&quot;}" /></entry><entry><title>Wrestling Python</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/wrestling-python/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wrestling Python" /><published>2017-09-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-09-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/wrestling-python</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/wrestling-python/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve had a cracking day today coding Python. I’ve done a spot of recreational coding with Python before but we’ve been given a set of exercises as part of our course work to help us get up to speed quickly, and it’s been great for building my skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve just looked through my code for the five exercises I’ve done today and I can actually see an improvement in my code between the first and the last exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the stuff I’ve got to grips with today has been:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;refactoring my code to make it object-oriented,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;organising my code into a python package (making it much more readable in the process),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.python.org/2.3/whatsnew/section-slices.html&quot;&gt;extended slicing&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;strong&gt;::-1&lt;/strong&gt; to reverse strings (these operators are not particularly intuative at first but are pretty powerful once you get your head round them)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pythonforbeginners.com/basics/list-comprehensions-in-python&quot;&gt;list comprehensions&lt;/a&gt; to iterate and evaluate over lists (can’t say I’ve &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; got my brain around these, but I’m getting there),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;getting offay with &lt;a href=&quot;https://git-scm.com/&quot;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; - I’m using it most days now and it’s becoming second nature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final thing. Isn’t &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/&quot;&gt;stackoverflow&lt;/a&gt; just the most brilliant resource for anyone learning to code? Thank you lord, for the good people who ask stuff that I too want to know, and thank you even more for the even better people who take the time to answer them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="coding" /><category term="python" /><summary>I've had a cracking day today coding Python. Here's what I've picked up.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000{&quot;feature&quot;=&gt;&quot;python.png&quot;}" /></entry><entry><title>A Short History of a Data Science Rookie.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/potted-history/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Short History of a Data Science Rookie." /><published>2017-09-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-09-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/potted-history</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/potted-history/">&lt;p&gt;I’m currently studing for an MSc in Big Data at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stir.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;University of Stirling&lt;/a&gt;, but I’ve done other stuff too. Here’s my potted history, work-wise at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dot-com-days-dot-com-nights&quot;&gt;Dot com days, dot com nights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In what sometimes feels like a previous life I studied ‘Computer Science’ (as it was called then) at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hw.ac.uk&quot;&gt;Heriot-Watt University&lt;/a&gt;, joined a tech startup as a software developer (employee number five) and after a while changed role to lead a small development team and finally a larger team, productising our in-house technology, a web application server and developnment suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this was at the height of the dot com boom. Exciting times. Espresso-fuelled all-nighters, crazy golf in the corridors, crazier deadlines, drum kits and bean bags and sky-high expectations, huge bonuses, testosterone and table-football. Exciting stuff indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except when it wasn’t, when the bubble burst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s when the recriminations, the tears and the redundancies started, and when the ‘sure-fire things’ that were our company and our product lay flat and dead in a puddle of their own excretions, lifeless and unrecognisable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, the true believers, the chosen ones, stood in shock and disbelief. What we had fully expected to happen hadn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There had been an understanding amongst all of us in the company about our collective futures, based on a set of assumptions about the world, the market and ourselves. The land of milk and honey lay just over the horizon. It would be ours. We’d reach it soon through diligence, intelligence and drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was widely accepted between ourselves, as an indisputable fact, that the world desperately needed what we were offering and that we could not fail.
This was largely down to a story we were told and which we believed, a story that in the end was instrumental in our undoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enduring metaphor of the dot com era was that of a ‘gold rush’. There was big money to be made from the internet and if you didn’t act quickly you’d miss out. Fortune favours the bold, as they say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our company, we were told, were making the picks and shovels that those neo-gold-prospectors needed to dig for gold in the internet wild west. You can’t dig for gold &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; picks and shovels. Everyone knows that. Duh. And, it was emphasised, it didn’t matter whether they &lt;em&gt;found&lt;/em&gt; gold or not, because they had already bought their tools from us. We’d make money either way. We couldn’t lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except no-one wanted to buy to buy our picks. Or our shovels for that matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d spent thousands of hours and millions of pounds building stuff that no-one wanted to buy. We’d pissed millions up the wall in a few short years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of it all I was just plain exhausted. I needed to do something different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;now-for-something-completely-different&quot;&gt;Now for something completely different&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what could be more different than primary teaching?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a year of teacher training in London, I moved backed to Scotland and started teaching in a primary school. After the excesses of working the testosterone-filled tech world of the late ’90s, adjusting to the life of a school was an interesting experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past five years or so my interest in technology has resurfaced, and I’ve started coding again, playing around with new languages, and exploring what’s possible with tools such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arduino.cc/&quot;&gt;Arduino&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://processing.org/&quot;&gt;Processing&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://p5js.org/&quot;&gt;P5.js&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four years ago, in a lightning flash of inspiration, I had the incredible idea that I could teach our pupils how to code, something that combined my interests in technology and education. I was pretty sure I was the only person in the world who had thought of this until I checked with Mr Google, who kindly informed me that I wasn’t. I was the millionth. Teaching kids to code was huge. It was all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undettered, I started a coding club in my school, loved it, and then shortly afterwards started two &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.coderdojoscotland.com&quot;&gt;CoderDojo&lt;/a&gt; clubs in disadvantaged areas of Glasgow, &lt;a href=&quot;http://coderdojoscotland.com/clubs/castlemilk&quot;&gt;CoderDojo Castlemilk&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://coderdojoscotland.com/clubs/bridgeton&quot;&gt;CoderDojo Bridgeton&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;now-for-something-completely-different-reprise&quot;&gt;Now for something completely different (reprise)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve taught for the last thirteen years. It’s time for something new. It’s time for something completely different. It’s time for data science.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>My potted history, work-wise at least.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000{&quot;feature&quot;=&gt;&quot;feature_image2.jpg&quot;}" /></entry></feed>
